Railway Labor Executives' Association Records 5484
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Railway Labor Executives' Association Records
1926-1976
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Railway Labor Executives' Association (RLEA)
5484
190.67 cubic feet
190.7 linear ft.
Records (documents), newspaper clippings, photographs.
This collection consists of the office files of the Railway Labor Executives' Association for the years 1930 through 1967 and select general and subject files for 1926 through 1976. The files include correspondence, court case reports, court decisions, legal filings, executive orders, reports of emergency boards, statistics, copies of legislation, political records, arbitration and mediation records, financial statements and labor agreements.
3120108
Biographical / Historical
The RLEA was founded in 1926 in response to the passage of the Railway Labor Act. Prior to 1926, there had been an informal association between the railroad labor organizations so that the various chief executives of the different unions could work together to form a unified course of action that would benefit all of their members. This group became more formalized immediately after the end of WW1. The U.S. railroads had been nationalized as part of the war effort, and the railroad labor organizations wanted them to remain under federal management, both because of increased productivity and because of better labor relations with the industry. The effort was ultimately unsuccessful, and the railroads returned to private industry; however, the railroad labor organizations had realized the need to have a united front to counter the carriers and industry groups and lobbyists.
On May 18, 1926, the chief executives of the railroad labor organization met in Washington D.C., formalized their association with By-Laws, and elected officers to serve the newly created RLEA. The original purpose, codified in the original preamble, was co-operative action to obtain and develop consistent interpretations and utilization of the Railway Labor Act. The RLEA was comprised of the chief executives of the 21 railroad labor unions, including the president of the Railway Employees' Department of the AFL, and each member got one vote, regardless of the size of their union. The organization was voluntary, so no member organization was bound by its decisions. Over the course of its existence, various member organizations withdrew and then re-affiliated with the RLEA.
From 1926 to 1938, the RLEA did not maintain an office, but the amount of work and its importance led the RLEA to open an office in Washington DC and employ a full-time Executive Secretary-Treasurer to run it. The RLEA did not engage in collective bargaining itself, but rather lobbied on behalf of its member organizations, securing such achievements as the Railroad Retirement Act and limiting unemployment for its members during the Great Depression. The RLEA's various areas of interest, such as retirement, safety, legal matters, were broken down into committees, each of which reported back to the executive board on the steps being taken in those areas.
Post WW2, the RLEA played a central role in the Marshall Plan, working with non-Communist labor organizations in Western Europe to establish labor policy and also assist in the work of rebuilding the European railroads. The RLEA was also a major factor in international labor union federations, and its decision to affiliate with the International Transport Workers' Federation (ITF) and to encourage the ITF not to join with the Soviet affiliated World Federation of Trade Unions was seen as a major victory for the west.
The RLEA, like its member organizations, did not allow African-American members. As such, it was only representing the interests of white railroad employees; black railroad employees were forced, for the most part, to work without recognized union protection. The exception to this was the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters (BSCP), who in 1948 began a series of successful legal challenges to the jurisdictions over various classes of work. As BSCP's successes in the courts mounted up, and the RLEA's member unions and the RLEA itself were being sued for discriminatory practices, the RLEA finally capitulated in 1950, and accepted the BSCP as a member organization.
In 1950, the RLEA joined with the AFL, CIO, and International Association of Machinists to form the United Labor Policy Committee. This committee oversaw the labor representatives of the Wage Stabilization Board.
In the latter half of the 20th century, the importance of the RLEA declined alongside the decline in the railroad industry itself. As its member unions either merged into single entities or disaffiliated from the RLEA its influence waned, as did the number of its members. The RLEA attempted to counter this decline with the purchase of a railroad at least three different times in the 1970s and 1980s, though they were ultimately unsuccessful in this venture. Ongoing internal battles between the remaining chief executives of the railroad unions further weakened the RLEA until in 1997 it disbanded, handing over its responsibilities to the newly formed AFL-CIO Transportation Trades Department.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1926-1976
Bulk dates: 1930-1967
This collection consists of the office files of the Railway Labor Executives' Association for the years 1930 through 1967 and select general and subject files for 1926 through 1976. The files are arranged in 14 series. Using the RLEA's File Guides (see collections 5552 and 5728), every effort has been made to arrange the records according to the original filing system for the Office Files (series II X). The RLEA arranged their records chronologically by year in designated record groups. These record groups are used for each calendar year. Each record group consists of numerous files, the majority of which are maintained from year to year. Only when the executive council removed a particular issue from their monthly meeting agendas, records related to that issue were removed from the record group.
Additionally, the RLEA filed their records with pages from the Agendas of their monthly meetings, annotated with the meeting minutes on that particular issue. As a result, the files themselves contain individual guides to the records contained in them. Agenda pages are not found in every file in this collection, for example neither correspondence files nor files containing printed pamphlets of legislation contain agenda pages, but the majority of the files possess this additional guide to the records.
This collection contains correspondence, court case reports, court decisions, legal filings, executive orders, reports of emergency boards, statistics, copies of legislation, political records, arbitration and mediation records, financial statements and labor agreements. Also found are foreign language newspapers, photographs, government documents, maps, time tables, merger proceedings, blueprints for office buildings, schematics for railroad facilities, and statistical data for the railroad industry.
This collection also contains extensive documentation of the Marshall Plan, the reconstruction of post-World War II Europe, mobilization of America's railroads during World War II, the Railroad Merger Era, and the beginning of the decline of the railroad industry post 1960.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Arrangement
Series I: Subject Files and Office Files, 1926-1953
Series II: Office Files, 1954-1959
Series III: Office Files, 1960
Series IV: Office Files, 1961
Series V: Office Files, 1962
Series VI: Office Files, 1963
Series VII: Office Files, 1964
Series VIII: Office Files, 1965
Series IX: Office Files, 1966
Series X: Office Files, 1967
Series XI: Railroads and Government: Legislation, Boards, and Policy Papers, 1935-1962
Series XII: Mergers, Acquisitions, and Abandonments, 1940-1976
Series XIII: Washington Job Protection Agreement, 1936-1963
Series XIV: Oversize Materials
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5300: Railway Labor Executives' Association Miscellany 5484 AV: Railway Labor Executives' Association Audio- Visual Material 5552: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5728: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 6087: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives 227 Ives Hall Tower Road Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheelref@cornell.edu https://catherwood.library.cornell.edu/kheel/
Compiled by:
Elizabeth Parker, February 09, 2018
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, February 09, 2018
Bankruptcy -- United States; Collective labor agreements -- Railroads -- United States; Contracting out -- Railroads -- United States; Discrimination in employment -- Law and legislation -- United States; Draft -- United States; Foreign workers, Mexican -- United States -- History; Grievance procedures -- Railroads; Hours of labor -- Railroads -- United States; Life insurance -- United States; Unemployment insurance -- United States; Japanese Americans -- Forced removal and internment, 1942-1945; Labor bureaus -- United States; Labor discipline -- Railroads -- United States; Labor disputes -- Railroads -- United States; Labor laws and legislation -- United States; Labor unions -- United States -- Political activity; Liability for railroad accidents -- United States; Marshall Plan; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- Railroads -- United States; Misconduct -- Railroads -- United States; Open and closed shop -- Railroads -- United States; Pipelines -- Economic aspects -- United States; Prisoners of war -- United States; Railroads -- Employees; Railroad employees -- Medical Examinations -- United States; Railroads -- Mergers -- United States; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions; Railroads -- Military aspects -- United States; Railroads -- Safety measures -- United States; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States -- Sources; Railroads -- United States -- Employees -- Sources; Railroads -- United States -- Abandonment; Railroads -- United States -- Consolidation; Retirement -- Railroads -- United States; Seniority, Employee -- Railroads -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Railroads -- United States; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Transportation -- United States; Vacations, Employee -- Railroads -- United States; Veterans' benefits -- United States; Wages -- United States; Wages -- Railroads -- United States; Washington Job Protection Agreement of 1936; Work assignment -- Railroads -- United States; Work rules -- Railroads -- United States; Working conditions -- Railroads -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Manpower -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Transportation -- United States; Lyon, A. E.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; AFL-CIO. Railway Employes' Department; AFL-CIO; Air Line Pilots Association; American Railway Supervisors Association; American Train Dispatchers Association; Association of American Railroads; Association of Western Railways; Atchison, Topeka, and Santa Fe Railway Company; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.); Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees; Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Brotherhood Railway Carmen of America; Brotherhood of Railway Clerks; Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters; Carriers' Conference Committees; Chicago and North Western Transportation Company; Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad Company; Chicago, Milwaukee, St. Paul, and Pacific Railroad Company; Chicago, Rock Island, and Pacific Railroad Company (1948- ); Commercial Telegraphers' Union of America; Congreso Panamericano de Ferrocarriles; Great Northern Railway Company (U.S.); Illinois Central Railroad Company; International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers, and Helpers; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers; International Transport Workers' Federation; Lehigh Valley Railroad Company; Labor/Management Committee (U.S.); Long Island Rail Road; Michigan Central Railroad; Minneapolis, St. Paul & Sault Ste. Marie Railway Company; Missouri Pacific Railroad Company; National Farmers' Union (U.S.); New York Central Railroad Company; New York, New Haven, and Hartford Railroad Company; New York, Susquehanna, and Western Railroad; Norfolk and Western Railway Company; Norfolk Southern Railway Company; Northern Pacific Railroad Company; Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen; Penn Central Transportation Company; Pennsylvania Railroad; Railroad Yardmasters of America; Railway Labor Executives Association; Railway Patrolmen's International Union; Southern Pacific Railroad Company; Southern Railway (U.S.); Texas & Pacific Railway; Unesco.; Union Pacific Railroad Company; United Nations; United States. Department of Agriculture.; United States. Department of Labor; United States. Department of State; United States. Department of the Treasury; United States. Department of Transportation; United States. Economic Cooperation Administration; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission; United States. National Mediation Board; United States. National Railroad Adjustment Board; United States. National Wage Stabilization Board; United States. Office of Defense Transportation; United States. Railroad Retirement Board; United States. War Department; United States. War Manpower Commission; Western Maryland Railway Company; United States. | Interstate Commerce Act; United States. | Railroad Retirement Act; United States. Railway Labor Act; Seasonal Farm Laborers Program
3120108
- Series I: Subject Files and Office Files, 1926-1953
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of the office files of the RLEA which, at the time of their accession, had been marked as "Inactive" and retained as subject files. They are arranged alphabetically by subject as per the RLEA's filing system. In some instances, groups of files are further arranged in record groups such as Government, Law, or Court Cases.
  These files contain the founding documents of the RLEA, including its original constitution and by-laws, as well as amendments made to those documents as the organization grew and changed. It also contains financial records, assessments of its member organizations, correspondence files for each of those organizations, correspondence files of various RLEA executives including executive-secretary Arlen E. Lyon, president C.E. Leighty, chairman James A. Phillips., and chairman George Harrison. Also found are correspondence files inviting unaffiliated railway labor union organizations to join the RLEA, records relating to the creation of the Washington DC office and the full-time salaried position of RLEA Executive-Secretary, and files covering the minutiae of running an office and lobbying Congress.
  Of particular interest in this series are the files documenting the U.S. railroad industry during World War II. As the lobbying and policy advisory organization for organized railroad labor, the RLEA was intimately involved in many aspects of supply and logistics on the home front during World War II. The records for the Office of Defense Transportation (ODT), the War Assets Administration, the War Department, the War Manpower Commission, and the Office of Defense Manpower Management-Labor Policy Committee all provide an extensive in-depth look at how the railroad industry functioned during war time, and how labor and the RLEA negotiated and lobbied to protect their members even as they sought to serve the national interest. These records also offer a picture of the size and power of the American railroad industry during its height of influence and reach.
  Of particular interest in the files from World War II and the immediate postwar period are the records of what was colloquially known as the Bracero Program. This program, managed by the State Department, the Department of Labor, and the War Manpower Commission, imported Mexican nationals to work in the U.S. as guest workers, both in agriculture and on the railroad where there were severe work force shortages. The program was started in 1942 when the United States and Mexico both signed the Mexican Farm Labor Agreement, and was extended with the Migrant Labor Agreement of 1951. This program was not popular with Labor, and the RLEA kept extensive files on the program. Even after the railroad portion of the Bracero Program ended in 1945, they continued to monitor the agricultural portion with representatives from National Farm Labor Union, AFL-CIO, including Ernesto Galarza, until 1959. The Bracero Program officially ended in 1964. The manpower crisis during the war encouraged the carriers to look to other sources of labor. This included proposals from various carriers to make use of interned Japanese-Americans as a source of cheap and ready labor. The RLEA quickly blocked that plan, claiming the risk of sabotage from these citizens (referred to as "Aliens" in the correspondence) was too great. The carriers also suggested employing prisoners of war, but were met with even greater opposition. Neither plan was put into effect. Additionally, in the files on the Bracero Program, there is correspondence in regards to the employment of African-Americans on the railroads, and how the use of Mexican nationals was negatively affecting their wages and chances of employment in an industry in which they were already subject to extensive discrimination from both labor and management. Finally, there are also files regarding the employment of women on the railroads, which include guidelines determining in which crafts women could be employed.
  The RLEA was also deeply involved in various postwar activities, both on the home front and abroad. Records in this series document the massive amount of trains and cars needed to move returning veterans from their disembarkation ports to their homes. There is also extensive documentation of the efforts to employee veterans in the railroad industry or to aid veterans in returning to their previous jobs on the railroads without loss of seniority or position.
  Abroad, the RLEA played a major role in the implementation of the Marshall Plan. The records of the Economic Cooperation Administration and the Mutual Security Administration located in this series document the rebuilding of European railroads and the intimate relations between the European railroad labor organizations with their American counterparts. On a personal level, the records on European nations in the "Foreign" subject heading contain letters from European railroadmen, writing for help from their American brothers. Some of these files, like the one on Greece, contain photographs of these men and their families. The RLEA and its member organizations spearheaded food and clothing drives and other charitable endeavors to aid people as best they could. On a national level, the records in the files on foreign countries and on the implementation of the Marshall Plan also contain detailed reports on the state of the various nations, the state of the railroad industry, and of labor. In particular, there is extensive reporting on Soviet, communist, and communist suspected influences in the various locations in which the RLEA had contacts and agents working on their behalf. These types of reports are not limited to European nations. The RLEA was also a major component of the United States' foreign policy in Central and South America. Their membership in the Pan-American Railway Congress was by appointment of the president and facilitated through the State Department. Additionally, it was this connection with the State Department that facilitated foreign worker exchange programs, where railroaders from other nations would come to the U.S. to study the American railroad industry. This series also contains records about the activities of communists in America, including select records of the House Un-American Committee.
  The beginning of the RLEA's role in international labor as discussed above in the organization history is documented in this series. There are extensive records created by the International Transport Workers' Federation including minutes of committee meetings, constitutions, reports on conference proceedings, and reports on trips to these conferences. There is also extensive correspondence between RLEA Chief Executives and their agents and counterparts in various sovereign nations.
  This series also contains documentation of the railroad industry in America. Statistics on all aspects of the industry, recorded by the ICC, are located in this series as are reports from the Department of Labor. Also found are extensive files on proposed legislation and enacted laws that are related to either the railroad industry or to the labor movement in America. (N.B.: For additional records on railroad legislation, see series XI). This series contains decisions by the National Mediation Board (NMB) and the National Railroad Adjustment Board (NRAB) determining which organizations have the legal right under the Railway Labor Act to represent classes of employees on different roads. There are also records on the implementation of the Union Shop provision of the Railway Labor Act and various amendments to that portion of the bill. Other areas documented include State level legislation, the building of pipelines and other means of transporting fuel, transportation of goods on waterways, and the passage of the Workman's Compensation Act. The records of various National Wage Movements may also be found in this series.
  Finally, this series contains legal filing by the RLEA in front of U.S. District Courts and the Supreme Court of the United States. Many of these cases established precedents for the implementation and adjudication of the complex and extensive laws and statutes governing the railroad industry and its labor practices. Slocum established that an employee may only seek redress from the NRAB except in the narrow case of common-law wrongful discharge, which was contra to previous interpretations. This decision was affirmed by Southern Railway v. Order of Railway Conductors. This decision remained in force until a public law was passed in 1966 to address the massive backlog of cases at the NRAB. The Supreme Court was also the body that overrode the ICC when it made decisions that failed to punish carriers for violating federal anti-discrimination laws, as was the case in Mitchell v. Rock Island Railroad.
  - Addresses, Miscellaneous, 1935-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American-European Railroad Relief, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American-European Relief: Sweden, V.J. Sjaholm, Representative, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes black and white photograph; Swedish newspaper clippings; and Swedish language materials.
  - American-European Relief: Trip of James A. Phillips, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American-European Relief: England, Frank K. Switzer, Representative, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Conferences: Railroad Executives and Union Chiefs (RLEA), September 29, 1949 and February 23, 1950 [folder 1 of 3], 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6a)
  - Conferences: Railroad Executives and Union Chiefs (RLEA), September 29, 1949 and February 23, 1950 [folder 2 of 3], 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6b)
  - Conferences: Railroad Executives and Union Chiefs (RLEA), September 29, 1949 and February 23, 1950 [folder 3 of 3], 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 6c)
  - Conferences: Railroad Executives and Union Chiefs (RLEA), 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)